Nicholas Ketz, PhD

Applied Research Scientist: Machine Learning, Data Analysis, Human Studies

■ nick.ketz@gmail.com • nickketz.github.io in LinkedIn:nickketz

Summary | Applied scientist developing machine learning solutions to advanced research problems. Interests in: understanding and developing intelligent systems (human and artificial); analysis and visualization of complex, high-dimensional data; quantitative approaches to art, music and aesthetics. Experience in academic and industrial approaches to research, product development and human studies.

EDUCATION/EMPLOYMENT

| HRL Laboratories Research Scientist: Information and Systems Sciences | 09/2016 - Present |
|--|-------------------|
| University Colorado, Boulder PhD: Computational Cognitive Neuroscience | 09/2010 - 09/2016 |
| New York University Research Assistant: Davachi Human Memory Lab | 09/2007 - 07/2010 |
| University Minnesota, Twin Cities BA:Physics, minor:Psychology | 09/2003 - 06/2007 |
| McNally Smith College of Music AAS:Music Recording/Production Engineer | 09/2000 - 05/2002 |

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

| Model Based Reinforcement Learning Domain adaptation in complex tasks | 01/2020 - Present |
|---|-------------------|
| Lifelong Deep Learning Sequential multi-task learning in deep neural networks | 09/2018 - Present |
| Closed-loop Neural Stimulation Device/algorithm development in humans | 09/2016 - 06/2018 |
| Cognitive Neuroimaging Experimental design/analysis of EEG and fMRI | 09/2007 - 09/2018 |
| Biologically Inspired Neural Networks Vision, Memory and Attention | 09/2006 - 09/2016 |

SKILLS

Deep Learning | Convolutional, Recurrent, and Generative Neural Networks. Deep Reinforcement Learning (model-free and model-based). Unsupervised learning (auxiliary tasks, semi-supervised)

Machine Learning | Non-differentiable Optimization (CMA-ES, MCMC), Probabilistic Inference (Clustering, Gaussian Process, Bayesian Optimization), Unsupervised Learning (KNN, PCA, ICA, t-SNE, UMAP)

Statistics | Parametric and non-parametric inference in linear and non-linear models: GLM, Random Effects, Bayesian, A/B (hypothesis) testing, time-series analysis, experimental design

Programming/Computing Packages | Python (PyTorch, Tensorflow, Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-Learn, OpenCV, Jupyter/Collab), MATLAB, R, bash, CUDA GPU, Git, Docker, Kubernettes, AWS, Azure

SELECT PUBLICATIONS/PATENTS

US Patent 2020 | System and method for optimized independent component selection for automated signal artifact removal to generate a clean signal

Nicholas Ketz, Matthew E Phillips, Praveen K Pilly; Scalable solution for removal of nuisance components in time-series data

ICLR 2019 | Sliced cramer synaptic consolidation for preserving deeply learned representations Soheil Kolouri, **Nicholas Ketz**, Andrea Soltoggio, Praveen K. Pilly; A novel framework for overcoming catastrophic forgetting by preserving the distribution of the network's output at an arbitrary layer

Journal of Neruoscience 2018 | Closed-Loop Slow-Wave tACS Improves Sleep-Dependent Long-Term Memory Generalization by Modulating Endogenous Oscillations

Nicholas Ketz, Aaron P. Jones, Natalie B. Bryant, Vincent P. Clark and Praveen K. Pilly; Brain-computer-interface for improving learning and memory using non-invasive neural stimulation during sleep